<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short treatise of the reason and cause why our mony [and] bullion have been exported for many years last past. With the way to prevent it for the future, and make mony more plentiful, vvithout raising the coyn. To which is added, something concerning the exchange, which is risen so high, that 'tis considerable profit at this time, to bring guinea's and mill'd mony from Holland. By a Well-wisher to England's prosperity.</title>
            <author>Well-wisher to England's prosperity.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60108</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829712</idno>
  <idno type="VID">34155</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248496465</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3637</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218086</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829712</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99829712e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60108)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34155)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2002:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short treatise of the reason and cause why our mony [and] bullion have been exported for many years last past. With the way to prevent it for the future, and make mony more plentiful, vvithout raising the coyn. To which is added, something concerning the exchange, which is risen so high, that 'tis considerable profit at this time, to bring guinea's and mill'd mony from Holland. By a Well-wisher to England's prosperity.</title>
                  <author>Well-wisher to England's prosperity.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for E. Whitlock, near Stationers-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVII. [1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: London, Octob. 17th, 1696.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Goldsmith's Library, University of London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Money --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  1689-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34155:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34155:1"/>
            <p>A SHORT TREATISE OF THE REASON and CAUSE WHY OUR <hi>Mony &amp; Bullion have been Exported,</hi> For many Years last past.</p>
            <p>WITH THE Way to Prevent it for the Future, AND MAKE MONY more PLENTIFUL, Without Raising the Coyn.</p>
            <p>To which is added, Something concerning the Exchange, which is risen so high, that 'tis considerable Profit at this Time, to bring Guinea's and Mill'd Mony from <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Well-wisher to <hi>England</hi>'s Prosperity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>E. Whitlock,</hi> near <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners-Hall.</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:34155:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34155:2"/>
            <p>HAving often consider'd the Mischief, that lately Attended us, by the Corruption of our Coyn, and the Difficulty and Pains the Parliament met withal, before they could fix on a Method to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate the same; and also the Hardship, as well as Charge, that have attended the Nation in general, by such an Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I have thought it a great Pity, as well as a Matter of Fatal Consequence to us, that after the undergoing of so much Trouble and Loss to obtain such a Noble Coyn, we should not be able to keep it in the Nation among us, to have the Benefit thereof: Which must be our Fate, if Care be not taken to prevent it. I do not question but against this Session of Parliament many Propositions will be on foot, relating to this Matter, that in divers Respects may out-do what I shall offer; but considering it may fall out, That one of a mean Capacity may happen to hit a particular Matter, omitted by another of greater Parts, have thought good to offer my Sentiments herein; and if I am out in my Judgment, in any thing here propos'd, I hope, it will be favourably construed, it being a general Good I aim at: And therefore shall esteem it worth all my Pains, if any particular thereof should prove a Service to the Publick.</p>
            <p>There need not be said much of the ill Effects that the Loss of our Mony will produce, it being well known to every one that understands any thing of Trade and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, That the same cannot be mannaged and carry'd on,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34155:3"/> as it now is, without Mony; for although formerly they were accustom'd to Barter, or Exchange, one Commodity for another, yet now the general way of purchasing any thing is by Silver or Gold; so that it's a common Maxim, <hi>That Mony in Trade is as Blood in the Body.</hi> Now if it fall out that there comes to be a Stop of the Circulation of the Blood, or by any accident it comes to be separated from the Body, that Body will quickly be destroyed. And we cannot expect but that will be the Consequence of our Trade also, if our Mony, which is the Life thereof, comes to be stopp'd from its due Circulation, either by those that endeavour to hoard it, or others who carry it away from us.</p>
            <p>And, if our Trade comes once to be spoil'd, the landed Man, as well as the Tradesman, the Country Man with the Citizen, nay, I may, say the whole Nation will quickly feel the Smart thereof; and this cannot be effectually pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented without coming to the bottom of things, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the Cause, and then it may be the easier to prevent the Effect, it being difficult for a Physician to apply a suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Medicine to his Patient, before he knows his Distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p>Now there is a common Notion gotten up among People, That the only Cause why our Mony and Bullion have been Exported, wholly arises from the Weight and Goodness of our Coyn; which would have been for ever prevented, if our Guinea's had been kept up, and the Silver rais'd in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to it.</p>
            <p>But I must crave Leave to dissent herein, conceiving that the Reason of its being carry'd away altogether springs from another Ground.—For, according to my Observation, the carrying away our Mony, and the Exportation of our Bullion, does not arise from the Weight
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34155:3"/> or Goodness of our Coyn, but because we have had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for more Mony these late Years in Foreign Parts than the Produce of all our Commodities that have been export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And when ever any People contract a Debt with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Nation, either by importing of their Commodities, or by the Expences arising by maintaining of an Army in another Country, and have not plenty of Commodities to Export and Sell at a reasonable rate, to suit a Demand in Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Markets, to produce Mony to defray those Expences, the Ballance must inevitably be sent in Mony.</p>
            <p>For, suppose, we were to receive from <hi>Holland,</hi> next Year, 100000 <hi>l.</hi> in Commodities, more than we should send thither, and should not have such Commodities as they had occasion for, to Export and raise Mony, to pay off this Debt, then it must be remitted or sent in Mony, and there is no help for it; for if we should raise our Crowns to 10 <hi>s.</hi> apiece, and our Guinea's to Forty Four, that would not prevent it; for then, instead of sending 100000 <hi>l.</hi> of our present Mony, we must send Two of this New, and so the same Quantity of Silver must be exported.</p>
            <p>For we, as well as other Nations, have no respect to the Denomination of our Neighbour's Coyn, but to the Quantity of Gold or Silver contain'd therein, and value it accordingly,</p>
            <p>And daily Experience demonstrates this to be true; for when a Foreigner buyeth any Commodities of our Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smiths, in <hi>London,</hi> and would pay for them in his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Mony, if the Goldsmith understands not its Goodness, he will make an Essay thereof, and after he has computed what Gold or Silver it contains, he will allow the Foreigner ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly for it, without having any regard to the Name or Denomination of it in its own Country.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:34155:4"/>
            <p>Likewise, if a <hi>Spanish</hi> Merchant should every Year buy of an <hi>English</hi> Clothier 20 Pieces of Cloth, at 9 <hi>l.</hi> apiece, which amounts to 180 <hi>l.</hi> and his Custom should be to pay for them 800 <hi>Spanish</hi> Pieces of Eight at 4 <hi>s. 6 d.</hi> which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly pays off this Debt; and thus they trade together for many Years: But, at last, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> should ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Coyn 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> and thereupon the Merchant should think to purchase 24 Pieces of Cloth for his 800 Pieces of Eight, he will be mistaken; for the Clothier would take no notice whether the <hi>Spanish</hi> Mony be rais'd or not, and thereupon will deliver no more Cloth for his 800 Pieces of Eight than he us'd to do; for just as much as they rais'd their Coyn, so much should we advance our Commodities when we deal with them: And if their Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions require more Goods from us than they send hither, the Ballance must come over to us in Mony, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing their Coyn will not prevent its being brought away from them.</p>
            <p>And as its with them so it is with us; for no Foreigner will take our Mony for more than the intrinsick value there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and if we have occasion to receive more Goods from them than we send to them, our Mony must go to pay for it, and our advancing the Coyn will not at all prevent it; for all the Effect an Advance of 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> would have in this respect, would be by sending 120 <hi>l.</hi> of the Advanc'd Mony to procure the same Quantity of Goods that 100 <hi>l.</hi> of our present Mony would do now.</p>
            <p>So that 'tis the Ballance of Trade that affecteth the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, either to raise or fall it; and the Course of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change wholly influences the bringing in or sending out of Silver or Gold: For when our Exports exceed our Imports and Foreign Expences, then the Exchange will always Rise, and keep up above a Parr; upon which it will be Profit to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34155:4"/> bring in Silver or Gold. So, on the contrary, when our Expences abroad and Importations exceed our Exportations, then the Exchange will fall below a Parr, and leave room to gain by carrying out of Silver or Gold.</p>
            <p>And when our Affairs are in such a Posture as to have the Ballance of Trade against us, our Mony will go away, notwithstanding it be rais'd 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> And also the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change cannot raise to a Parr (that is, for us to receive by a Bill in <hi>Holland</hi> the same Weight of Standard Silver that we deliver here) which we do not when the Exchange is at 33 <hi>scill. 4 gro.</hi> although many esteem it to be then at a Parr.</p>
            <p>For 100 <hi>l.</hi> of our Mill'd Mony, paid here, weighs, in Standard Silver 386 <hi>ounc.</hi> Troy <hi>wt.</hi> and I receive for it in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> at that Exchange, 333 Duckatoons and a third, and the Weight of each Duckatoon is 1 <hi>ou. 22 gr.</hi> and being <hi>4d. wt. 12 gr.</hi> better than Standard, the whole makes 355 <hi>ou. 13 d. w. 12 gr.</hi> of Standard Silver; by which means we lose 30 <hi>ou. 6 d. w. 12 gr.</hi> of Silver, which at 5 <hi>s. 2 d. per</hi> Ounce is 7 <hi>l. 16 s. 8 d.</hi> loss to us, and the Difference is more when we are to receive Bank-Dollers, and to be paid in other <hi>Dutch</hi> Mony the loss is still greater.</p>
            <p>And when the Exchange is so low that we receive, by a Bill, less Silver there than we pay here; the Difference that it amounts to, is clear Profit to those that will export any Silver, deducting out the necessary Charges that attends the sending it over, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By which means the Silver that is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported from <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>West-Indies</hi> and elswhere, cannot come to the Mint to be coyn'd, it yielding a better Price to the Merchants for Exportation, as the last seven Years Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience has made appear.</p>
            <p>Now, having laid down my Sentiments of the Cause, why Silver and Gold is Exported, I shall endeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate (with submission to better Judgments) what I think will be a suitable Remedy to prevent it.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:34155:5"/>
            <p>The first and great means, to help us in this Case, would be, to find out (if possible) a way to secure our Shipping, that thereby our Foreign Trade may be preserv'd, and our Ships pass and repass in Safety, without being so often taken by the <hi>French;</hi> which Losses do greatly affect the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For altho' they have not been much taken notice of, by reason the People were wealthy, yet, if they should still continue, they will quickly be felt with a Witness; for notwithstanding some are so ignorant as to say, If all should come home safe, the Merchants and Traders would grow too rich; concluding, that what they lose extends only to themselves: Not considering, That if he loses his Effects, 'tis not his particular loss only, but the Nation is so much the poorer by it. And that is not all, but great part of these very Goods, that are many times taken, would be export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again, and raise Mony, beyond Sea, to defray our Charges; which would keep our Coyn among our selves. And thus the whole Nation is greatly aflected by the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Losses; and here, the Trade, that would bring Riches to the Nation, being obstructed and discourag'd, by the continual Losses, the Treasure that we acquir'd by our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Trade, comes to be exhausted, the greatest part of which (if not all) might have been kept among us, if we could by any means have shear'd clear of these Losses: For (it's thought) that notwithstanding the Expences that the War brings to us, if we could preserve all our Foreign Trade, the Ballance would be on our side, and instead of sending any Silver away, to pay the Army, or for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities imported from other Parts, we should not only have enough to answer all our Occasions abroad, by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce of our Merchandize, that would be exported, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so should have to spare; which would be brought Home in Mony, and so naturally come to the Mint to be coyn'd. But
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34155:5"/> the Merchandize, that should effect this, being taken, our Mony and Bullion must go to answer our Occasions abroad, which that (had it come safe) would have done without it.</p>
            <p>For instance, suppose several <hi>Turkey</hi> Merchants send 100000 <hi>l.</hi> worth of Cloth to <hi>Turkey,</hi> which costs us little, it being the Product of the Nation, and Labour of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; which being sold there, is return'd in rich Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to the Value of 150000 <hi>l.</hi> and being safely arrived here, they sell in <hi>England 100000 l.</hi> worth of these Goods, and 50000 <hi>l.</hi> they ship off for <hi>Holland</hi> or elswhere; which they sell there for Mony, and intend to have it home for their Occasions here: Now, suppose the King's Agent, that remits Mony for the Army, should pay the Merchants their 50000 <hi>l.</hi> here, and take their Bills, to receive it beyond Sea, then this Sum comes hereby to be sav'd to the Nation, and the King's Occasions are answer'd, and the Mony preserv'd among us.</p>
            <p>But, on the contrary, this Ship goes safely, and coming home, is taken into <hi>France;</hi> and thereby the 50000 <hi>l.</hi> that the Government wants, must go in Silver or Gold, by reason the Merchants have lost their Goods, that should have produc'd Mony beyond Sea; and so cannot furnish the King with Bills, unless they send Mony to do it. And not only so, but many of these very Commodities, that were taken in this Ship are so much wanted here, that a great deal of Mony must be sent into Foreign Parts to purchase them for our own use.</p>
            <p>Likewise, if a Merchant remits Mony to the <hi>East Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> to purchase, Flax, Hemp, Pitch, Tar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Vessel comes to be taken; 'tis not only the Loss thereof that barely affects us, but having occasion for these Commodities, we must send away another Sum; and if that meets with the same Fate we must still send again.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:34155:6"/>
            <p>And thus we may esteem the Loss of every Ship (in a manner) as though we had lost so much Mony; and then, if we look back and consider the many Ships and rich Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes, that have been taken, and the immense Sums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny those Effects would have produc'd us in Foreign Parts, had they safely arriv'd; it may take off the Cause of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, why so much Bullion has been exported, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sent away.</p>
            <p>For some are of Opinion, That if the <hi>East India</hi> Ships, that were taken last Year, had come home safe, they alone would have produc'd us, beyond Sea, over and above what we should have us'd our selves, near 500000 <hi>l.</hi> which would have sav'd us so much Silver or Gold: And if those Ships alone would have wrought such an effect; what would our Trade in general do, if well managed, and could be safely secur'd from all parts of the Universe, where we are concerned in Traffick and Commerce? for the Product of our Land is naturally so good, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities and Manufactories we raise, are so valuable in themselves, that were they rightly improv'd in Trade, with all the other Advantages this Island enjoys, far beyond our Neighbours, they would produce plenty of Riches to the Kingdom. For, before these Wars great Quantities of Gold and Silver were annually brought to the Mint; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing our Guinea's went at 21 <hi>s. 6 d.</hi> and our Mill'd Mony was then as heavy and valuable as it is at this Time: Which was the Ballance of Trade that was then in Favour to us; for we Exporting more than we did Import, the Ballance we received in Silver or Gold, which were coyn'd into our Mony: And we may always conclude <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> thrives when store of Gold and Silver comes of it self to the Mint. And as soon as ever a Method can be fix'd on to secure and incourage our Trade, that thereby it might be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34155:6"/> improv'd to the utmost ('tis thought) there would be suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Imployment, not only for all our own poor People, but for many thousands more than we have in the Nation.</p>
            <p>And then, the next thing that would greatly add to the Riches of the Nation, would be, to find out some Ways, and have them put in Execution, to set the Poor to Work, both in Improving of Land, and for Increasing our Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factories, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for Land without the Labour and Husbandry of the Inhabitants is good for little: So also the Wooll and other Materials, that are the Product of the Land (of which all our Rich Commodities are made) are worth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, comparable to what they are afterwards brought to, by the Labour and Pains of the People; so that, that which produces the Riches to this Nation chiefly consists in the People's Labour, notwithstanding the Goodness of its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Production. And, it may be concluded, there is a great Treasure lost by suffering so many thousands of Poor People to spend their Time in Begging and Idleness, when scarce any Person, either Old or Young, (that are in Health,) but may do something, according to their Capacity, towards making up our own Manufactories: which being exported, have Value sufficient in themselves to attract Gold and Silver from most Parts of the World.</p>
            <p>Now the next thing that would be a means to help to keep our Mony here, is, the retrenching of our Expences of all Foreign Commodities; both those relating to Suste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance as well as Apparel, for whatsoever we could save by our Frugality, in these things, we should have so much the less to pay abroad.</p>
            <p>And seeing there is so much Need of all the Helps imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to keep our Mony in the Nation at this Time, 'twould be well if all People would abate their Extravagant Living, and endeavour to spend as little as possible, of all Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities that are of a Foreign Growth.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34155:7"/>
            <p>Another material Thing is to provide the Army with Necessaries from hence, both Provision and Clothing, which would save us a great deal Yearly; And although it may be something more Chargeable, yet that is no valuable Objection; because the Materials being of our own Growth and Product, the Mony will be spent among our selves, and all that we could save this way, would be Profit to the Nation, and also increase and incourage Trade among our selves.</p>
            <p>Now before I conclude, I shall add something more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Coin, which is so much exceeding the former, that People are very unwilling to part with it: And that which makes them the more fond of it, is, our still having 2 sorts of Silver Mony, <hi>viz.</hi> the Old Unclipt Mony, and this New: And there are some that if they have not enough of this Old hammer'd Mony by them, will deferr their Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments till such Mony comes to their Hands; when at the same time, many have enough of both Sorts to make up their Sum; whereas, if there was but one sort of Coin, it would become more common, and People would not covet so much to lay it by: But whilst we have two sorts of Mony going in Trade, and one is inferior to the other, either Intrinsically, or in the Estimation of the People; the worst Sort will always be offered in Payment, and the other (as much as possible) lock'd up from coming abroad; and this was lately seen between Clipp'd Mony and Guinea's, for when People esteemed Guinea's better than Silver, they kept up the one, and paid away the other: But when Guinea's got up to about Thirty Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, then most Payments throughout the Nation were offered to be made in them, and but little Silver Mony was to be had; and during all this time, the Old Mill'd and Unclipp'd Mony that now comes forth, never
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34155:7"/> appeared at all; by which it is manifest, that the Mony which the People esteem the best, they will always en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keep by them.</p>
            <p>It would therefore be very requisite to have all the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipp'd Mony called in also, and Recoined, which would likewise prevent a great many vexatious Disputes and Differences about Mony, and make the Negotiating of all Affairs in Trade far easier for People, and for ever put an end to that wicked Device of Clipping of Mony, which has brought so much Mischief to the Nation, and is feared will not be effectually stopt, until the Unclipp'd, Hammered Mony be all taken out of their way: For many begin already to impose Mony that is a little Clipp'd, which if it once take place among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it will not be stopp'd until it has brought another Inconveniency upon us.</p>
            <p>And this may be done without any Trouble at all, now the Mints are set up in several Parts of the Nation; and if an Act should pass, That after such a prefixt time, as the Parliament in their great Wisdom see meet, all the Unclipp'd Mony that should be paid the King on any account whatsoever, should not be issued out of the Exchequer again, but be immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately melted down, and carried to the Mint to be Coined; which would quickly put an end to all the Unclipp'd Mony in the Nation; and the Loss to be placed on the Acts provided for the Difficiency of the Coin.</p>
            <p>Now the Consideration of this leads me to another sort of Payment that greatly hinders Mony from coming abroad, and that is the <hi>Bank of England</hi>'s Notes, that are daily offered in Payment instead of Mony: And many of these very Persons that offer them, have, at the same time, both Gold and Silver, which they will not bring forth, if they can by any means put off these Bills in the room thereof.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:34155:8"/>
            <p>And 'tis now become a common (not to say wicked and unjust) Practice, especially among Retailers, if they have no Notes by them, will purchase some with their Mony sometimes at 17 <hi>l. per Cent.</hi> Advantage to pay their Debts, that ought, in Justice and Equity, to be answer'd <hi>in specie,</hi> which many times proves a grinding of the Face of the Poor; for these Notes are given in Payment from one to another, until they light into an indigent Person's Hand, who is forced, through his urgent Occasions, to sell them at 16 or 17 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Loss.</p>
            <p>Now the true Reason why People are so earnest to put away their Notes, and keep up their Mony, arises from the difference between the Value of the one and the other; and as long as there remains a Disparity between them, the one will always be plenty and the other scarce. And if some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be not done to prevent this growing Evil, the Mint may Coin, and the Country expect a plenty of Mony there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and fall short of it at last; for the Clothier, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> comes to Town, hoping to receive Mony to carry home to pay his Labourers; and being put off with a Bank-Note, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to lose so much by it, goes home without any: For want of which, many cannot keep the Poor at Work.</p>
            <p>Now the best Cure (that I know of) for this Disease, would be by making their Notes as currant and valuable, in the Eyes of the People, as Mony it self; which (I conceive) cannot be done but by the Members of the Bank being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to pay all the Demands that can be made upon them; for there is nothing (in my Judgment) that can make Notes, or Paper-Credit, equal to Mony, but by their being answer'd by Mony, whenever they are demanded, which was the only thing that made them pass as Mony at first, and gave them their original Life and Acceptance among People: And if once there is a stop in Payment of any sorts of Notes, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34155:8"/> Credit of them immediately declines, without having a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the ability of the Subscriber thereof.</p>
            <p>And therefore if it be objected, That 'tis impossible for the Bank to procure Mony to answer their Bills, or make them equal to Mony, then they will greatly hinder Mony from coming abroad, which produces many ill Effects to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; upon which it will be much better to have them pass in no Payment at all, which would cause Mony to circulate and come more plentiful in Trade than it does now.</p>
            <p>And 'tis evident by this one Instance that Mony would come abroad more if those Notes did not hinder it, <hi>viz.</hi> After the Bank made a Demurr upon the Payment of their Notes, the People began to refuse them upon Foreign Bills of Exchange, upon which several Merchants addressed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the Government about it; and many People al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd, That unless they would take Bank-Notes in Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Bills could no way be paid, there being not <hi>specie</hi> to be found to answer them; but after about 14 days Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration the Matter resulted in this, <hi>viz.</hi> That Bank-Notes were no lawful Payment of Bills, and every Merchant must find Mony to do it himself: Upon which no Body that had a Foreign Bill, would take any thing but Mony for Payment thereof: And daily Experience declares these Men were mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken, for most Merchants have ever since, and do still, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to find Mony to pay their Foreign Bills withal, no Body offering now to pay them, with any thing else but <hi>specie,</hi> by which means great Quantities of Mony have been brought forth, that had not appear'd if Bank-Notes would have done in the room thereof; and 'tis thought if they were not offer'd in Payment for any Inland-Bills also, the Clothiers and other Manufactorers would get their Bills in some time (altho' with Difficulty at first) paid in Mony; which would be sent and distributed among the Country-People.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:34155:9"/>
            <p>It's therefore worth the serious Consideration of those concerned in the Bank (of which there are many worthy Members) if they cannot raise Mony to answer their Notes, to endeavour (if possible) to find out some other way to make them equal to Mony, which would give them a Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency every where, and make them at this juncture an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to Trade in general; but if it cannot be brought about, they had better, for a publick Good, give over giving out any more Notes; and those that have 'em in their Custody, should keep them, and not offer them in Payment any more till the Bank are capable to comply with the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, or by any other way they are made equal to Mony.</p>
            <p>Another Thing that will make Mony more plentiful among Trades-People, is by having their Clipt Mony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into Mill'd and Current Mony; for there are many People in City and Country, who have both large and lesser Quantities of this small Mony by them, which is now alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether useless to them, which if they had in Current Coin would be very serviceable to them in their Trade and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness. It would therefore be of great advantage to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, to have this Matter immediately settled: And if Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty was given to all People to bring their Clipt Mony to the Mint, where the same should be melted down and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayed, and left to be Coined, and afterwards deliver'd to the Owners in course, according to the Weight thereof; and that there be a Tally given to every one for about 12 <hi>d. per</hi> Ounce, towards the Difficiency, placed on a good Fund, which would be 12 <hi>l.</hi> allowance for every clipt 100 <hi>l.</hi> that weighs 20 <hi>l.</hi> Weight: But let the allowance be more or less, it ought to be done by Weight, because it's to be fear'd that many ill-minded Persons have clipt Mony on purpose to have it taken in by the Government by Tale; but it being taken in by Weight, not only disappoints them in their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34155:9"/> wicked Designs, but the more they Clip it, the more Loss they will sustain thereby. And, besides, considering that a great deal of the remaining part of the clipt Mony is shifted from the first Owners at 15, 20 and 30 <hi>per Cent.</hi> allowance, 'tis unreasonable that the Nation should make good the whole Loss, and give such an advantage to the present Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessors thereof: But to have some Incouragement given to bring it to the Mint by Weight, seems very reasonable; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause those who have any Remains in their Hands, and others that have taken it from 10 to 25 <hi>per Cent.</hi> allowance, will be too great Losers thereby, if nothing at all be done in it.</p>
            <p>And that which will further encrease Mony would be, by continuing the Incouragement of bringing Plate to the Mint; there having been pretty large Quantities brought in already by the allowance of Six Pence <hi>per</hi> Ounce, given by the late Act of Parliament to any one that should bring in the same before the 4th of <hi>November</hi> next; but the Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences not being so secured to be paid as gives a general Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, greatly obstructs this having a good effect.</p>
            <p>Now if they were placed on a good Fund, or rather paid down in Mony, after the Plate was Coined, it would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce great Quantities to the Mint in a little time. And if there was in like manner an Allowance of Sixpence <hi>per</hi> Ounce given, to encourage the bringing to the Mint all Silver whatsoever (melted Silver only excepted) during the space of one Year, it would be of great Service to make Mony more plenty.</p>
            <p>Another Thing that makes Mony more scarce, is a hope that our Mony-hoarders have gotten, that it will be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced this Sessions of Parliament; for, notwithstanding several Persons have desired to borrow Mony of those that have had Quantities by them, at more than 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34155:10"/> upon the Security of clipt Mony, Plate and Lands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they have refused it; by which 'tis concluded, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to have the Mony advanc'd. Now as soon as ever this Expectation comes to be put an end to, a great deal of Mony, that now lies dead, would come forth into Trade again: And although many may propose an advantage to themselves thereby, yet it would not be such a Benefit to the Publick, as People have imagined, for no less would be sent out of the Nation, as is before made appear. And those who conclude, That 100 <hi>l.</hi> would go further in Trade, after it is called 120 <hi>l.</hi> are much mistaken; for as our Mony is heavier and mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> valuable than it was, so Commodities we see are cheaper also (unless a few particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Things, which upon some extraordinary Occasions are always dearer or cheaper;) and supposing the Trade of the Nation could be carried on with six millions of clipt Mony, the same Trade can be better managed with four millions of New; because the four millions of New, will purchase more Commodities than the six millions of Clipt did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for about a Year ago, when Clipt Mony went cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, and Guinea's were at 30 <hi>s.</hi> apiece, that Wooll which was sold then for 36 <hi>s.</hi> a Tod, has been sold for less than 20 since the Regulation of the Coin; but if the Mony would purchase as much as it does now, after it was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, I do not see that it would be any prejudice to do it; but seeing it will not, makes it a manifest Loss not only to Landed-men, but to many others also: For suppose I have 600 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> let out upon Lease, which is paid me in this present Mony, with which I can maintain my Family, and lay up 100 <hi>l.</hi> a Year: But if I think to do so when the Mony is advanced I shall be disappointed, because I shall buy no more Commodities with this 600 <hi>l.</hi> of Mony that is advanced 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> than I could with 500 <hi>l.</hi> of this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34155:10"/> present Mony, and so I lose 100 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> by it: For 'tis not the calling a Crown-piece 6 Shillings, that will make it purchase more than it does now; for as soon as that goes for six Shillings, the Commodities that I use to buy for a Crown, will presently advance to six Shillings also: Which will likewise be a great Loss to all the Poor in the Nation, unless they advance their Wages upon it. And, besides, if it should be advanced to induce People to bring out their Hoards, we may fall short of our Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations in that respect also.</p>
            <p>For the greatest Reason why People lay up their Mony more now than they did before, arises from a Diffidence they have one of another, upon which they will not give such Credit as they were accustom'd to do; which (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) will not be altered by an advance of the Mony; but 'twill wear off by degrees, as Trade encreases and is secured, and Mony comes to be more common and plenty. And considering the many Confusions such an alteration will produce (unless we were sure to be Benefitted by it) 'tis better to keep the Mony to the Standard, than any ways to alter it. For although many People have been uneasie, because the Coin was regulated at this Juncture, yet when our Difficulties are over, not only us, but the next Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration will have the Benefit thereof; and if it had not been done, (in all likelihood) it would have center'd in the Ruin of the Nation. And the keeping our Mony to the Standard will prove otherwise, than many (through Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) have imagined; for we see already that 'tis Loss at this time, to carry out of the Land either Guinea's or mill'd Mony, by reason the Exchange is risen so high, that it is above a Parr in Silver, and much more in Gold, by which means it is Profit to bring over from <hi>Holland</hi> either of them. And the Reason why 'tis more Advantage to bring
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34155:11"/> Guinea's than Silver, is because the Silver contained in 22 <hi>s.</hi> of mill'd Mony is worth more in Value, and will yield more beyond Sea, than the Gold contain'd in a Guinea.</p>
            <p>And if the Exchange keeps up, our Silver and Gold will not be sent out of the Land, (except sometimes upon par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Occasions) but they will be carried to the Mint as formerly; notwithstanding it has been aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmed, That Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in Bullion was worth more than Silver in Coin, and therefore 'twould never come to the Mint; which was a great Mistake, as appears by Matter of Fact; for it being Loss to carry it away, makes Silver in Coin worth more than Silver in Bullion; and Ingots of Silver that were sold for between 6 and 7 Shillings <hi>per</hi> Ounce, are now lying in the <hi>Tower</hi> to be Coin'd into Mony, and 'tis expected that Quantities of Gold will be brought over in a little time: But seeing the Exchange cannot raise to a Parr but by the Ballance of Trade (except sometimes occasioned by parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Causes that are not lasting) it may be concluded, That as soon as ever the Scale turns, and it comes down so much below a Parr, as to afford a Profit by Exporting of Silver, then our Mony and Bullion will go from us again. Now the Preservation of our Shipping and Foreign Trade, I shall once more humbly recommend as the chiefest Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient effectually to prevent it, and furnish us with Mony sufficient to answer all our Occasions both at Home and Abroad.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 17th, 1696.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:34155:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>